Market structure one of the most
important aspects of price action
trading and while it seems simple most
people get it wrong so buckle up because
in the next 10 to 15 minutes you're
going to know everything you need to
know to become a master of Market
structure and stick around to the end
because there's something waiting for
you there that will take your learning
to the next level so what is market
structure it's just the way the market
moves uptrends consolidation and
downtrends these are the three phases of
Market structure and this is what they
look like the idea is we buy through
uptrends sell through downtrends and
stay out during consolidation during a
trending move not consolidation moves we
get two phases impulses and Corrections
impulse moves are PR Trend moves and
Corrections are pullback moves why does
this happen because the market is an
auction in an uptrend for example there
will be points where buyers want to buy
but they're not happy paying the current
price to actually buy that contract or
asset so buying slows in the short term
easing the market until it reaches a
price that people are happy to pay when
a good buying price is met people buy
and the next impulse starts again quite
simple right so so why is it so hard to
understand and what makes it difficult
well the first place people go wrong is
in Reading highs and lows incorrectly to
read structure we look at higher highs
higher lows lower highs and lower lows
but because markets move across
different time frames sometimes we can
get caught up looking at the wrong lows
and the wrong highs to avoid this we
want to view structure as waves so
instead of looking at every small up and
down move we want to look at structure
in big phases like this this keeps you
in tune with the overall trend Direction
instead of getting you lost in every
small push and this leads me on to the
second Point substructure versus swing
structure the waves we just drew out are
swing structure and the small moves that
happen within are substructure it is
possible to take advantage of these
smaller substructure moves as they are
valid Trends inside of the larger Trend
itself we're going to talk about this
very soon so let's have a go at mapping
structure for this example we're going
to GB AUD on the 1H hour time frame now
we can see we had a trend shift here
shifting us into an uptrend now we're
going to map the swing structure so in
terms of the Swing structure we are
seeing multiple breaks of structure
which are taking us to the upside and we
can also clearly see the market is
making higher lows along the way so this
is clearly an uptrend it's not a
downtrend now how exactly do we Mark the
swing structure are we going to consider
every tiny little Nuance in the trend no
we are not we are going to move with the
bigger picture and view this as waves so
there we have Wave 1 that's the impulse
wave two that's a correction wave three
is the next impulse wave four four is
the correction wave five is another
impulse wave six is a correction and
then wave seven would lead us all the
way up towards this point just here
because this really is not too much of a
viable breaking structure being just a
wick and this would actually signify the
larger wave so you've seen there how we
Mark out structure as a wave instead of
actually trying to look at every single
little move now sometimes when I'm
teaching someone they come to me and
when they're in their early days they're
actually looking at every single little
movement like this and considering
considering this is the larger Trend
Direction and then getting confused
because they're like well the Market's
changing direction every few seconds how
am I supposed to keep up with this well
in reality we're not we just want to
move with the big picture we don't need
to worry about little candle movements
like this and the intricacies of each
small move what we need to do is focus
on that big picture remember earlier I
mentioned the concept of substructure
the smaller Trends inside of the larger
Trend well we can actually trade these
as their very own Trends so breaking
down structure even further in this
example we can start to look for the
smaller opportunities inside of the
bigger move so now working with the same
piece of structure that we just looked
at in that structure mapping example we
are going to look at the substructure
and swing structure of the market so
let's mark on the swing
structure and now let's mark the sub
structure the swing structure is the
impulse moves and the substructure is
the correction moves the pullbacks okay
so as you can see although the larger
trend is bullish we do see smaller
bearish opportunities happening within
we can see that we have a valid
downtrend actually happening inside of
the correction this is where we can take
advantage of the substructure to take
trades that are counter to the higher
time frame swing Trend but entirely
valid using a lower time frame so for
example here inside the hourly we could
drop to the 15minute and look for
15minute bearish opportunities
throughout this structure so for the
sake of example I'm going to dig into
this movement here and show you where
the substructure opportunity came in
okay so using this piece of price action
we can see we have the impulsive
movement this was the larger hourly move
and now we are looking for a corrective
move now of course we do not want to
execute upon any trades until the market
sentiment has shifted so being on the
15minute we would want to see a
15-minute break in structure which would
come at this level now if we get that
all good we can go for a substructure
move if we don't get that that's fine we
will just be continuing with the higher
time frame swing
structure now as you can see we've just
broken the trend here by forming a lower
low with a body closure so what we could
do now is look for opportunities to sell
through this Valley 15-minute Trend so
why are we doing this if we know that
the high time frame is bullish well the
reason for that is simply because we
have a valid lower time frame Trend so
this actually comes back to the fractal
nature of the market now the market
moves in a way where the same patterns
are repeated across multiple time frames
and this is a great example of that we
can actually see a valid hourly Trend
but we can also go and see a valid
15minute Trend both of which may provide
valid trades now when you're taking a
trade like this because we're moving
against the higher time frame even
though we're moving in a valid 15-minute
Trend here we do want to make sure we
are employing a break even strategy or
trailing stops or doing something that
will save us when the market doesn't
reach our targets because obviously if
the high time frame trend is bullish the
high time frame trend has more weight
that means that we're not always going
to get our targets filled therefore
meaning sometimes our trades May reverse
after moving in profit so we need to
make sure we're protected from that and
in an Ideal World locking something in
as well through trailing stops so as you
can see see this trade has now played
out and we would have actually added
here 3.5r that we wouldn't have seen if
we weren't using this substructure swing
structure methodology now you could
obviously refine this to your strategy
or execute the trade however you want
the concept I'm trying to show you today
is just the trend so you can see that
both the biggest swing structure and the
smaller substructure can provide
opportunities for traits the hard part
is differentiating what is Swing
structure and what is substructure and
the best way to do that is by looking at
the market as waves the next rule you
should consider is how far you should
look to take your substructure trades
before taking profit you shouldn't try
to extend substructure moves past the
highs or lows of the Swing structure
moves so if we're in a swing uptrend and
we are taking a substructure sell we
should look to take profit at or before
the demand Zone at the bottom of the
Swing structure move this way we know if
the market continues to move in the
uptrending fashion we are out of our
sell move before we get destroyed this
way we capitalize on the whole pullback
or correction but we don't try to take
the market too far and instead we keep
moving with the larger swing Trend if
you enjoyed that hit the link in the
description that's going to take you to
my free course where you can learn more
about Market structure supply and demand
liquidity macroeconomics and other Core
Concepts that are going to tenfold your
trading performance trading with the
trend is the most secure way to make
money in the markets and now that you're
armed with the knowledge on how to do
that I suggest you go and back test
build up a data set and then learn from
your personal perception of the market
with that being said don't procrastinate
don't waste time get to
work